do
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to the 80th live
episode of ask abhijit it's great to be
back with you all again
today as you know is the 125th birth
anniversary of one of india's greatest
sons one of india's greatest freedom
fighters subhash chandra bose
so let us take a moment to remember the
great man's contributions
to
the india that we live in today
so the freedom that you all enjoy today
it's not because of mr mohandas gandhi
or mr jawal nehru or mr patel or any of
the freedom fighters you are taught
about in school
the freedom whatever semblance of
freedom we are enjoying today is because
of
subhash chandra bose a genuine freedom
fighter not a fake freedom fighter
subhash chandra bose was a genuine
freedom fighter who put his life on the
line they put his life on the line he
put his
reputation on the line he actually faced
bullets
he looked death in the eyes mr gandhi
never did that mr gandhi never faced any
bullets neither did mr nehru or whoever
else
the so-called great freedom fighters of
india mr bose did that he had skin in
the game there is this very important
concept in leadership
skin in the game
a leader must have skin in the game
which means when something goes wrong
the leader must be the first to face
that
in in naval warfare the captain always
goes down with the ship so that is
something mr bose believed in
and it's because of mr bose that the
british
that the evil genocidal blood thirsty
barbaric british occupiers of india it's
because of its suppose that they finally
decided to leave india they decided it
was not safe anymore for them to remain
in india they decided that it's enough
we need to leave india immediately it's
because of mr bose that this happened
and had mr bose
won
then the india you live in today would
have been a very different country it
would have been a genuinely free country
today india is a partially free country
it is still under foreign occupation
there is so much mental colonization low
standards mediocrity foreign
constitution foreign laws foreign
institutions hindu phobia everywhere
it's because mr bose lost but he lost
while doing what he was doing best for
the country
so we need to
take his work forward and make india
truly a free nation
mr bose was a man of
very high standards today india is the
nation of gandhi and
a nation of mediocrity and low standards
if you want to truly honor mr bose raise
your standards
stop wasting your time step stop wasting
your life stop gossiping stop watching
bollywood do some real work
live up to his standards
so
that's what i would like to stay say
just to start off with to pay tribute to
the great
sebastian rabos on his 125th birth
anniversary
and now let's take some questions i am
at your disposal for the next 90 minutes
or so so ask me your best questions
let's see what questions we have today
okay let's take this one
it's by pinakpani joshi uh
in indica megasthanis the greek
ambassador to the mauryan empire
writes about indian history and 2000 to
300 200 to 300 bc indian situations
current source
of it reliable to know our ancient
history
okay so what he's asking is that is that
a reliable source of information see we
have so little information today about
the
ancient times in indian history
all of our own records have been
destroyed a thousand years ago in the
destruction of our great universities
and the burning of our great libraries
so whatever little information we have
we have to make do with that so one of
the sources of information for the
mauryan era of our
history
is the account of megasthanis who was a
greek ambassador to
to
to the mauryan empire
uh he was a resident in partly putra i
believe which is present day patna and
he wrote a reasonably detailed account
of indian society and
the country
at that time so uh what he says is well
because of the positive information we
have to treat all of this information as
very precious
and we can glean whatever we can from
that so i think it's a reasonably uh
factual account of the
of the country of the civilization of
the culture of the time it is more it is
written more like a
more like a tactical military account an
observation of how things are you know
that sort of thing so it's reasonably
factual and what's interesting is that
he writes about the uh
the division of labor in indian society
so any society which is a functional
society has a division of labor without
division of labor you can't have a
functional society so what megasthenes
wrote was that indian society was made
up of seven classes seven divisions
nowadays you would call them castes
right because of the
colonial terminology so in the days of
megasthenes he observed that there were
seven different classes of people in
india including the scholars which would
today be called the brahmins then you
had the administrators you had the
advisors and ministers of the king you
had the warriors you had farmers you had
other
i don't remember exactly what the the
entire division was like but there were
seven divisions seven major divisions in
society so that's an interesting thing
that uh this uh
account of megasthenes tells us a lot
and he also
explicitly mentions the fact that there
was no slavery in india no indian was
ever a slave so there's a lot to be to
to learn from this account and it you
know it
it kind of goes it kind of contradicts
everything that is written about india
in the colonial
uh
historiography
so i think it's a it's a
good and
informative source
about our ancient
history
okay atharva says how can we become a
dharmic country without a monarchy what
elements of monarchy and theocracy can
we bring in the government i'm 16 years
old in class 12. i act like your videos
very much thank you
you don't need a monarchy for a dharmic
society
you can have a constitutionally dharmic
country right
your constitution and laws can be based
on the precepts of dharma
and you can have a democracy india has
throughout his history been a democracy
in some way or the other
you had the mahajanapada era which was
essentially democracy you had the pala
kingdom in bengal whose first founder
king i believe in the seventh or eighth
century was elected democratically the
people were fed up of the lawlessness in
the in this in the
kingdom and they elected a person or man
from their own midst as the king and he
was the founder of this uh i think the
parlor dynasty in bengal so we always
had democracy
the people always were
paramount
in indian society so we certainly can
have that again instead of a king we can
elect
presidents prime ministers or whatever
you want to call them
and you can have a constitution and laws
that are dharmic in nature instead of
dharmic like they are today it's very
simple
right so we don't need monarchy at all
we can have a presidential system or a
prime ministerial system or whatever you
want as long as the constitution and the
laws are dharmic you have a dharmic
society which would be a great
improvement
in the way the country is run
okay all right where do we have
what else we have wisdom bro my dear
friend
uh most of the talented hindustani and
karnatak artists are living in india to
teach abroad in the crappy bollywood
music is gaining more audience
how can we save our music you know
indian culture needs safe state support
throughout india's history indian
culture whether it is the performing
arts the dramatic arts whether it is the
indian classical music whether it is
indian dance painting architecture
whatever it
has always needed state support
india's kings emperors queens rulers
have always supported indian culture and
that's why indian culture thrived so
much it needs patronage any form of art
or culture needs patronage either from
up high or from the grassroots
in the absence of such patronage
culture dies out it withers away and
after independence there has been a
studied and concerted effort from the
part of the government to starve out
indian culture so we have these
organizations like the sangeet narak
academy which don't make any difference
in the
in the real world scenario and that's
all so they support that and that's it
our work is done
so because of that indian classical
music which is the richest and greatest
musical tradition in the history of
humanity it is withering out today it is
dying out it is dying out
it is way way richer and superior and
older than any other form of of music
anywhere in the world indian classical
music whether it is hindustani music or
carnatic music right
so it's just withering away it's dying
out there is no support for it there is
no
support for for such music for for this
form of art among the public because
there is no exposure to it anymore for
the past 50 to 70 years right so the
only music people listen to is this
garbage which is called bollywood music
and that doesn't even represent indian
culture at all it represents middle
eastern culture and foreign cultures it
does not represent indian culture
neither does bollywood music neither
does bollywood dance represent indian
culture but that's the mainstream today
and i i see this all the time every
single indian man woman or child seems
to have a bollywood song going on in
their head 24 by 7.
and when you have some celebration
is whether it's a religious celebration
or a wedding or whatever they play this
bollywood
music which is an insult
to your ancestors and their culture
so that's what what's happening today
how can we save our music we need state
support
and uh
there needs to be exposure exposure see
today nobody knows even
the the teenagers and kids up to don't
even know what indian classical music is
they've never heard it they've never
seen indian classical dance so we need
exposure and it's the government that's
needed that needs to do this we have a
ministry of culture and god knows what
else what are they doing what are we
paying them for why are we paying taxes
the ministry of culture and tourism is
the least performing the worst
performing ministry in the whole country
in the entire government they should be
ashamed of what they've been doing for
the past how many years
so it the the
what needs to happen is we need state
support for indian culture classical
music hindustani
music carnatic music or whatever right
because it's dying out
and it's it's so beautiful so
i i wish the government would wake up
maybe sack the minister whoever is in
charge and have somebody else who
actually wants to perform and do it make
a difference in the world
okay will indian people accept one party
rule because i think netaji like that
indian people will accept everything
indian people accepted jesse attacks
indian people accepted the rule of the
british so why why won't indians accept
one party rule indian people are sheep
today they will accept anything that you
dump on their heads
they accept corruption day in and day
out they accept mediocrity they accept
forced conversions they accept the
missionary schools converting their
children to whatever culture and
religion
indians accept everything indians have
no standards indian don't care indians
don't care indians are like sheep so
they will accept one party rule if you
impose that on them also as long as my
little life is the same i don't care
so yeah indians will accept that
indians will accept anything if tomorrow
china comes and takes over india the
indians will accept that also because
indians have lost all
lost their spine essentially
it's very sad
survey says why do india's neighbors
especially pakistan and china hate and
trouble india despite it being the most
democratic and tolerant nation as
compared to other nations
[Laughter]
i mean i'm i'm wondering how do i answer
this question
they don't hate india because of
democracy and tolerance
they why does china china doesn't hate
india
china doesn't hate india china fears
india's potential
so china the chinese communist party
wants to take over the world and rule
the world and one of the major
impediments
to this is india india is the only
nation in asia that's powerful enough
strong enough to potentially
push back against china and even
potentially defeat it that's what the
chinese are trying to destabilize india
it's nothing to do with hatred
it's nothing to do with democracy or
tolerance or any such thing
it's all about real politics and
geopolitics
and the pakistanis hate india because
well they hate themselves
pakistanis are indians but they pretend
that like they are something else
see if you take if you look at the
various muslim countries in the world
let's take turkey if you take islam out
of turkey there is turkish culture and
language and all that that is still
there so it is purely turkish if you
take out islam from egypt you still have
egyptian culture egyptian civilization
and all that but if you take islam out
of pakistan what is left
so they pretend to be arabs they pretend
to be turks and they hate who they are
and because they hate who they truly are
that's why they hate india and they they
also hate indian culture and hinduism so
in the case of pakistan it's a genuine
hatred in the case of china it's about
geopolitics right
and
no matter how tolerant and democratic
india will be
these attitudes will persist it's
nothing to do with democracy or
tolerance it's something else
all right um
it says give respect to bollywood just
like you give respect to the great nehru
yes i guess of course ashley thank you
for reminding me uh the great great
exalted
bollywood film industry and music
industry right
why did mahatma gandhi deny his wife
medicine mr gandhi had very high
high ideals
so
yeah it is true that uh when his wife
what's her name kasturba
when she was ill in her last days and
when she was uh
on the precipice on the verge of death a
simple
antibiotic like penicillin would have
saved her life but i think mr gandhi
said no you don't
that should not be used and that's why
she died i think that's what i've heard
and when
mr gandhi is a mahatma right mahatmas
have different standards
so i suppose that's one of the
characteristics of a mahmut to deny your
wife
uh life-saving medicine i suppose
what else i mean
i have no other answer
mr mahatma mohan dasta mahatma
is it possible that china can equip
pakistan with hypersonic missiles which
will give pakistan an edge over india
what can india do about it it is
certainly possible that china will can
equip pakistan with various missiles the
chinese have equipped pakistan with
nuclear weapons
the chinese are the worst proliferators
of nuclear opens right
so uh they have equipped china pakistan
with nuclear weapons
they have transferred north korean
missile technology to pakistan
in the future they may transfer
uh
a few hypersonic missiles to pakistan to
give an edge over india and all that so
what can india do about it what india
needs to do over the next five or ten
years is break up pakistan
it is high time that india ends this
problem
at its western border
we have to find a way i don't care how
it is for the leadership to do this
you have to find a solution it doesn't
matter how you find it what solution it
is but you have to find it that's the
job of a leader no excuses
we have waited for 75 years it is time
for india in the next five to 10 years
maximum to fragment pakistan to break up
pakistan into its component pieces
and give independence to sins to
balochistan to pashtunistan to punjab
and
whatever else we would like to do it is
time i have nothing against the
pakistani people i i wish them no harm i
wish them peace and prosperity and
whatever else they want
okay but pakistan in its present shape
and form is a threat to all civilized
societies and to humanity so it is for
india to solve the problem
and to preclude all this nuclear
blackmail and hypersonic missile threats
and all india in the next five to ten
years has to break up pakistan in one
way or the other doesn't matter how find
a way
that's why we elect leaders so that they
can find a way to solve india's problems
so this needs to happen so that's what
india needs to do about it and in the
meanwhile what india can do is we can
also proliferate and sell our missiles
to other countries so now it's happening
we are selling the brahmos missile to
the philippines aren't we we may sell it
to vietnam as well let's let's encircle
china
with batteries of brahmos missiles the
chinese fear the brahmos messiah so it's
one of the deadliest cruise missiles in
the world so let's do that
let's repay them in the same coin that
they are paying us with
so that's what india should do in the
meanwhile in the interim
is elon musk a fake futurist no elon
musk is not a futurist at all he's an
entrepreneur he's a businessman and he
is uh
someone who is developing futuristic
technologies
through trial and error and he i don't
think he's a fake futurist uh
his worldview is the western world with
the capitalist worldview and it's a
pessimistic worldview which actually is
a bit realistic because if you look at
the way the planet is going today
capitalism is ruling the planet
it is destroying the environment the
oceans are choked with plastic the
atmosphere is being destroyed there is
pollution everywhere there is a threat
of nuclear war nuclear holocaust right
now we have a couple of situations in
europe in ukraine in kazakhstan that
could
become big conflagrations
depending on the actions of the various
actors whether it's the russians whether
it is the nato alliance which is
essentially the us so there are lots of
problems so what elon musk wants to do
is he wants to give humanity options
so
maybe we can colonize mars and maybe the
richest of us can go and live there if
there's something which goes wrong on
our planet that sort of thing so i don't
think he's a fake futurist he's putting
all his money where his mouth is
and one should appreciate what he's
doing
right he's investing he's taking
enormous risks with all his money he's
not investing in other companies and and
keeping his money safe he's investing
all of his money into the riskiest
ventures he can think of which is spacex
tesla and all that so i i respect the
guy he is
really doing something that
that is important i would say yes it is
certainly important
all right
why does the current government not
investigate the subhash in the rabose
case i think we will have to ask the
current government
i don't have an answer uh many uh
many governments have made noises about
this that we should declassify the thing
and
reveal the truth about what happened to
mr bose
and scholars like mr anusdar generator
ghost have done a lot of
scholarly research and essentially
cracked the case more or less
so why does the current current
government not do it well i
don't really know we need to ask the
government about this so
the standard refrain is that it will if
you declassify certain things then it
will cause problems from a geopolitical
perspective and it will cause problems
in our relations with certain friendly
countries and so on that's a standard
refrain and answer that you get all the
time
how much of that is true i'm not sure
this is something that happened long
long time ago
uh so
yeah i think the best
the person
to whom we need to ask is somebody from
the government right so
let's see if we can get somebody from
there and ask this but i personally
don't
have the answer because i do not speak
on behalf of the government
okay
uh
what else do we have
ayan says saw a letter going around on
twitter written by shri shitharam goyal
calling nithaja's vision as a union of
fascism and communism not fit to lead
well i haven't seen this
and there's all kind of stuff going on
on social media i don't know how true or
false it is much of it could possibly be
fabricated and since i have not seen
this personally
i would not like to comment on this if i
see this personally and i can study it
and examine it then maybe i could form a
certain informed opinion about this i
personally haven't seen this
so i think it is just prudent for me to
not comment about something i have not
seen and examined personally but what i
do see nowadays these days
is a lot of
western commentators
who are
passing judgment these days about savash
and rabos
you have all these so-called south asia
experts who are saying it is a dangerous
thing that india is now
honoring subhashin therapose the man who
allied with the japanese and the nazis
and all that because you know it is
somehow a bad thing that he took the
side of that he sought help from the
nazis
and the same and it's not just these uh
western commentators it is also their
local
uh
local indian
tail wagging sepoys and coolies who are
also echoing these sentiments nowadays
on social media
there is this ndtv anchor called vishnu
some is going around crying about this
and extolling the virtues of the
colonial regime the british occupation
force of india or india and all that the
thing is this
mr bose was a nationalist he's he did
everything from the perspective of
national interest he did not care about
his reputation he did not care about his
life
he
cared about india in the national
interest and he and it is a logical
thing to conclude
it like this that if
my enemy the occupying power the
oppressing power is the british then i
should alive with the enemies of the
british in order to get rid of them
i don't care what they're doing
elsewhere
my enemies enemy is my friend it's my
ally and that's the logic which makes
sense historically which has always made
sense historically he employed the same
logic and that's why he allied himself
temporarily
with the japanese and with the
nazi regime
in order to achieve the limited
time bound goal of defeating the british
i see nothing wrong with that and all of
these people who are currently
moaning about the honor that subhash and
rebels is getting
they will never say a single word about
the genocide that the british committed
in india at least a hundred million
deaths through artificial famines the
latest of which was perpetrated by
winston churchill in the 1940s at least
four million million bengalis
were deliberately and systematically
starved to death by winston churchill
who stole their rice and sent it to the
west
to aid the so-called war effort against
the nazis
so
when it comes to
vincent churchill these people are quiet
and they they will not condem any of his
actions any of his genocide genocidal
brutal barbaric bloodthirsty actions
but on the other hand they want us to
condemn the nazis and condemn so
washington was because he allied with
the nazis this is called double
standards
right so my possession is very simple if
you don't care about what churchill did
to my people i don't care what the nazis
and the germa and the japanese did to
your people not my problem very simple
bose was a nationalist he cared only for
india he did everything for india he put
his life on the line for india he
sacrificed everything for india we must
honor that
that is that is called genuine
real politic and that is how a freedom
fighter should
that is the real definition of freedom
fighter
so that's what i can say as far as
fascism and communism is concerned these
are tools
what is the definition of fascism
anything you don't like his fascism
right that's the that's the the the
current uh
uh
that's the
the way things are portrayed anything
if the indian government does anything
especially if it is the modi government
then it has to be fascism
there is no definition of fascism
whatever they do is fascism that's how
it is
right
so i don't care about any of this
nonsense
according to me mr bose was india's
greatest freedom fighter far greater
than mr mohandas gandhi or mr jawal
nehru or anybody else
and so
that's what i can say i don't care about
fascism communism any of that if if what
mr bose
embodied was fascism then we need to
support that
because because he supported india
all right
where else are we
what else do we have
in your previous streams you said
external forces installed dictators in
african nations can you explain this and
and name those forces you know karl marx
in the 19th century he spoke about the
invisible hand he said there is an
invisible hand that controls
world affairs global geopolitics and it
is a group of people that we cannot see
who are acting behind the scenes and
they actually are the ones who
uh influence events worldwide and the
shape
of
of geopolitical actions he called it the
invisible hand now he is not a he was
not a conspiracy theorist he was a
realist he is considered to be one of
the greatest thinkers of the west and
the philosopher and all that right so
even today you have such things now
forget about africa for a minute let's
talk about india
yes it is true that external forces in
the past
150 years have been interfering in
africa uh they are the ones if you see
let me let's take a look at the map of
africa shall we
so here we are if you look at the map of
africa there are all these straight
lines is it natural for
geographical boundaries political
boundaries to be straight lines
everywhere
can you see straight lines straight
lines everywhere in africa
it's because the european colonizers
when they left africa they don't they
did not even bother to draw maps
properly and and make space for tribal
divisions they just randomly drew
straight lines and get go out of the
country but they kept on influencing
events after they left so what happens
in africa is that because of the
straight lines
various tribal groups
have been uh cohesive tribal or social
units cultural unit force for centuries
they found they find themselves on
different sides of the boundary and
their allegiance lies to their tribe and
their culture not to their artificial
nation that have been created by the
west and that's why you have so many
civil wars in africa and that is great
for the west because they can keep
interfering in africa and keep
exploiting resources from africa that's
what they've been doing and now was the
chinese who are doing that right but you
will see the same thing even in the
middle east straight lines
right once again a legacy of colonialism
of of the west you will see straight
lines even here
yeah
which is erstwhile
the erstwhile boundary between india and
persia
now
forget about the for forget about africa
for a minute let's talk about india
in india you have constant
foreign interference in the internal
efforts of india right now
as of today there are certain forces in
the world that are way too powerful even
for india
they are way more powerful than the
indian government than the iranian
government than than the german
government
than than the
then the uh you the government of the uk
there are certain forces that are so
powerful that they can overpower any
country anytime
and they keep interfering across the
world and telling countries how to
conduct their internal and external
affairs
it is done via a variety of means for
instance in india we have all these ngos
we have hundreds thousands of ngos that
get substantial amounts of foreign
funding
now do you think money
is given for free
do you think money is given without any
expectation
no
these are all
means
of interfering in the internal affairs
of india
for instance the indian judiciary
entertains these pils public interest
litigations
that come in from various ngos and all
these ngos are funded from abroad
millions of dollars billions of dollars
so this is direct interference in
india's internal affairs
isn't it
and these ngos are allowed to run
unchecked in india the government of
india
for whatever reason is unable to stop
their activities because of arm twisting
from certain very strong forces from
abroad
you have billions maybe tens of or
hundreds of billions of dollars that are
being poured into india every year for
the sake of conversions to foreign
religions
this is again
external interference in the internal
affairs of india these are
movements to re-engineer the
demographics of india this is called
demographic engineering
that's what's happening right now in
india as we speak
so it's not just africa it's happening
right here in india and these forces are
way way too strong
the indian government is no match for
these forces
neither is any other government in the
world actually
it's only certain countries like china
and russia that are trying to push back
against these forces
right
so india needs to become stronger until
that time there's going to be constant
interference in india's internal affairs
india's foreign policy is also
not an independent foreign policy
actually
right
but
it's not entirely independent but yet
india is making the right moves in
foreign policy by allying with nations
like france for instance
if you look at france you will
understand where the foreign
interference is coming from if you have
some understanding of geopolitics so so
that's what's happening
so when it comes to africa the these
external forces have been
installing puppet dictators for decades
and whenever a dictator becomes too big
for his own boats he's taken care of
and there have been certain nationalist
movements certain nationalist
politicians who came up in africa
patrice lubumba for instance they were
assassinated knocked off
right and then a convenient dictator is
put in place
so that's what the americans have been
doing for that's what the western
countries have been doing even france
has been doing that in various other
european countries in africa
and nowadays even the chinese are doing
it the chinese are doing it elsewhere
right so that's what's happening the
recently the german
[Laughter]
uh the german chief of navy he came to
india a couple of days ago he became a
very big furore
and he spoke his mind openly
he said the chinese have been doing this
they are installing puppet governments
everywhere they are propping up
dictators it doesn't matter what they do
as long as they allow chinese
the chinese government access to their
country's resources so that's something
the chinese are doing now but it's what
the west has been doing for
at least a century in africa
so
that's what's happening and those are
the the forces at work
how we can do corruption in politics
just join politics and we'll be corrupt
politics is all about corruption
especially at the lower levels
right now the only clean politics in
india is at the central government level
completely clean i can i am certain of
that
but everywhere else
okay i will not say everywhere else but
in many places in the lower levels of
government you have corruption so if you
want to do corruption in politics just
join politics at any level and you will
be able to indulge in corruption i know
you are asking the opposite
but
the answer also
will help you explain what the opposite
is
how can we end corruption in politics it
has to happen top down
now that we have a
clean
uh
government at the central level they
need to find ways
of starting to clean up politics from
the top down level so one level below
one level below one level below like
that it's going to be a long process
it's not going to be an easy process but
it has to happen if india has to become
a great culture great civilization again
right now we are merely a west italian
nation state a truncated broken country
we have to become a civilization state
again
so for that we will have to
fight corruption and destroy it from its
roots
right
all right um
so much safety says is it true that
mankind started from africa but the
expansion started from india only we
hear old indian kings had huge empires
extending even ahead of middle east is
it true
so
when we talk about indian kings who had
large empires it's in the past two
thousand years three thousand years
maybe five thousand years
but the history of humanity starts a
million years back
right so there's a
difference in the chronological uh time
frame that you're looking at right
that's what i'm saying
so indian history when we're talking
about expansion out of india migrations
out of india that happened uh in the
rig vedic era maybe before that and
maybe uh definitely after that we had
kingdoms like uh the regions of uttar
kuru tara madra which is north of india
and west of northwest of india and so on
so central asia essentially
and this entire region was indian uh
dominated if you are indian origin
people living there but that is all in
the last
maximum 10 000 years or so which is what
we have uh
which is what our ancient texts record
all these different migrations out of
india the migration that happened at the
end of the battle of the ten kings when
those other kings were defeated and they
were forced into exile they had to go
out and so on and so forth so yes we had
big empires kingdoms etc in central asia
north of the middle east and so on and
so forth yes but that is something that
is at most in the last ten thousand
years most likely in the past five six
seven thousand years
we had the yamnia expansion out of india
which is now almost certainly out of
india because r1b is most likely 99.9
in indian origin haplogroup
right so again the yamnya expansion out
of india which conquered all of europe
it also happened about six thousand
years before today but the out of africa
migration is known from genetic data to
have happened about 80 000 between 80
and 70 000 years before today
right
and the oldest evidence of homo sapiens
anatomically modern humans
dates back about 250 000 years before
today
it is found in some parts of africa the
oldest evidence of our species
right
so
from the best evidence that we have
genetic evidence and archaeological
evidence for the best evidence
we have
we can say that humanity
our species homo sapiens started from
africa now lots of people don't agree
with me
fine
but you need to base your beliefs not on
sentiments and feelings but on data
if tomorrow we find older data older
evidence of homo sapiens from india i
will change my mind
then i will say okay we have new
evidence now and maybe it started from
india fine but show me the data
as long as we don't have data from india
which shows that humanity started in
india we have to agree with whatever
existing data we have which all points
towards africa
now some people say that according to
our yuga system the ramayana happened
nine crore years ago and all that
so to those people what can i even say
right so so let's not go into that but
it is from all the evidence that we have
archaeological and genetic evidence the
story of humanity
starts in africa if new evidence emerges
that changes the story we will also have
to change our understanding of history
but from the data we have it starts in
africa
right
what is the current position of
development of the northeast region in
terms of infrastructure projects
for the past 70 years the northeast
region of india has been neglected
right
ever since independence the north east
was marginalized totally neglected no
development happened there are no
industries no infrastructure no jobs
nothing stepmotherly treatment uh the
congress regime once even bombarded i
think
was it was it
mizoram i think it was mizoram using the
indian air force so the
the attitude towards the northeast has
been that of a stepmother
for the past almost 70 years in the past
10 years or so i can see a lot of change
happening there
now we are developing more
infrastructure there for instance the
state of manipur let's take the state of
manipur do you know where it is let me
show you where it is
this is manipur in the so-called
northeast of india it's the far east of
india so for the past 70 years there has
been only one highway that connects nor
manipur from to the rest of india and
that highway comes through
through uh
through the state of nagaland
and you may not have heard of it but
there have been repeated blockades of
manipur through nagaland and through
naga dominated areas of manipur
repeatedly months at a time years at a
time where nothing is allowed to come
into manipur
and so the the price of a gas cylinder
would go into several thousands of
rupees and medicines would become
unavailable that sort of thing so that
is the kind of treatment that was done
to the northeast and they have their own
internal problems which are historical
problems
uh so that's why we have this only one
highway that goes to manipur from india
can you believe it so now today we have
a different another highway that comes
through assam and now there's also a
railway line that is being built
and manipur is going to become most
likely the gateway to northeast india
through the city of moray
to the little town of mori which is at
the border of india and
myanmar
so there's gonna be a railway that will
connect india
through mouri
to myanmar
to thailand
to malaysia and it will go all the way
to singapore and hopefully we will also
have road connectivity other
connectivity to laos and other parts of
southeast asia it is high time we do
that
so for the past
ever since so our so-called independence
we have developed nothing no
infrastructure that connects and get to
other countries india is like a
landlocked country no development of any
kind in the border regions no
connectivity to other countries either
through railway lines or through road
lines
and
nowhere is it more apparent than in the
northeast so nowadays in the past
decade or so ever since the current
government came into into power there
has been an emphasis on developing the
northeast whether it is in the the
states of manipur nagaland etc
or whether in rural position all it is
now being undertaken on a priority basis
which is a very good thing we need to
spend another 20 30 50 years doing this
and make the northeast as developed as
the rest of india if not even more and
in the northeast can become india's
gateway to south east asia why not
so that's kind of what's happening
nowadays the signs are good this
government is doing the right things and
it needs to continue
okay
um
shenzhen versus bangalore both are these
countries silicon valley but why
bengaluru is so unplanned while shenzhen
the younger city is much more planned
it's because see let's
how do i explain this
see it's like this this the central
government wants to develop india
there's no doubt about it they are doing
everything they can to create
infrastructure you have
dozens of kilometers of highways that
are being built every single day
connecting various parts of india new
airports are being built or new railway
lines are being built they are doing
everything they can from their side
the central government to develop india
to construct infrastructure at as fast
as possible right
but there are certain things that come
under the state state government
and state governments have a mind of
their own india says that we have this
federal system which is our great
strength it is not our great strength it
is our greatest weakness
and what you find is that at the
municipal level
the the the the district level state
level
you have politicians who don't who often
not always but often don't care anything
about the country they are only
concerned about their own personal
whatever
and
often they they are they they don't like
what the state goes what the central
government is doing so they want to show
the central government in a bad light so
they will
ensure that there is no development
locally
so no infrastructure no town planning
they will keep the city in a state of
disrepair and so on
i'm just saying in general i don't know
about bangalore who is in power there
and all i'm not quite sure but
that's the kind of thing there is
so it's not just about bangalore
bengaluru there are many such cities
where the
local
government deliberately keeps the thing
in a terrible condition
right
so if the central government had direct
control over cities like bengaluru or
whatever else
things would change very fast
but since it is not the case that's why
the people
in those cities are stuck with whatever
government they have with whatever
government they have elected
and then they are reaping the benefits
of that
so there is too much federalism in india
in china you have one party that rules
everybody it is dangerous it's it's but
it's also it also has the benefits that
you can see the whole country is being
developed equally i mean not the whole
country tibet
is not the case but yeah all the han
regions
of china are being developed in this
manner is there any scientific
explanation of ghosts well i don't have
any scientific explanation of ghosts
yeah i'm not the right person to ask
this
sorry sorry
uh what are your views on artificial
womb technology well i haven't heard of
this this is the first time actually i'm
actually coming across this but uh
i suppose it's bound to happen
everything will eventually be artificial
artificial hearts artificial livers
artificial kidneys artificial wombs also
i suppose
so i haven't come across this until now
but it is certainly something that
science will
develop sooner or later
so yeah you can have artificial corneas
artificial joints for instance
artificial hips and knees and all that
you may even have nowadays you have
artificial meat right vegan meat that is
exactly the same as a
chicken or whatever else so everything
will eventually be
available
and and
manufactured through artificial means so
i suppose you may even have artificial
rooms in the future
right that's what i can say
uh why does every government task in
india take so much time please pick sir
it's because of the bureaucracy
see the bureaucracy the entire system in
india which is a legacy of the british
raj
is designed to help though to to to
see the intent and the purpose of this
system which the british created
was not
to empower and help
the citizens and the country
it was to empower the political or lords
which is the british
now after the british left
the political overlaws became the
congress party and whoever was in power
and the system was never changed the
system was the
system of oppression the system of
foreign occupation so today also the
same system process it's as if we are
still occupied by a foreign occupying
power but the foreign
occupying power is our corrupt
politicians nowadays not all of them are
corrupt but many of them are corrupt
and the bureaucracy
and the
administration
they are exactly
the same they are run in exactly the
same manner and they have the same
attitudes as their predecessors had
during the british raj they did not see
themselves as public servants they saw
themselves as public overlords
and very often they don't like the
policies the government is implementing
so they try their best to slow it down
and they are lazy they are underpaid and
they are mediocre people
they have no motivation they have a job
for life and it doesn't matter what they
do how badly they mess up
they're going to have the job for life
so in in this kind of environment of low
standards in mediocrity everything will
take time
everything is going to be slow there is
no urgency
there is no consequence for messing
things up
if a government servant a bureaucrat
were to be fired for for wasting time
if that
system were in place then everything
would suddenly speed up
but according to the i think in some
articles of the indian constitution
these guys can't be fired
government employees have a job for life
essentially the most you can do is
suspend them but they will still get a
salary and they will still be able to
come back to the job eventually so this
is the system that is entrenched in
india and it is so hard to remove it
because if the government makes any move
to change the system the entire
bureaucracy will go on strike and then
there will be no governance in india
so everything
india is a nation
of 1.3 billion people who are hostages
to the governance system to the
bureaucrats a nation of hostages nothing
else
so that's why
it takes so long everything's everything
takes so long every good thing is
delayed
every good decision of the government is
demonized
and very often
they have to take it back as you as you
see and the people are so brainwashed
the thing everything the government does
is bad farm laws were bad bad for the
farmers you idiots
they were not bad for the farmers they
empowered the farmers
but no
we will we will watch ndtv and various
podcasters
and we will believe what they say
because we don't have a mind of our own
we will just absorb other people's
opinions and use them as our own
opinions
you can read the farm laws the actual
text and make your own judgment but you
will not do that
you will listen to ndtv and make your
own decisions based on that so you know
i'm not saying all of you are like this
but i have come across people like that
many people like that
unfortunate so this is the level that we
have in india and that's the level you
see in the government as well
especially among the bureaucrats
and the
so-called public servants
all right mayank says in your talk with
dr ishtak
the noted anchor and panelists were
quite
quite gandhi centric in their approach
can you share your experience about that
and would you be collaborating with dr
ahmed again see i don't know mr dr ahmed
personally is a pakistani
origin
academic who lives and works in sweden
or something he's written a book or so
but i don't really know much about him
so i was on this
discussion of sorts on
on
a small youtube channel
called
what was it called the argumentative
indians right
and uh
the the panelists were the dr ishtak
ahmad a lady from the jnu there was this
this former
advisor to the prime minister of india
called mr sudhindra kulkarni
and there was this anchor i don't
remember his name and they the what was
the discussion about it was about
something to do with partition or
something i don't remember the exact
topic
but what i
observed was
there were at least a couple of
pakistanis on the
at least a couple of pakistanis on the
panel
and they were all so much in love with
mr gandhi
gandhiji this and mahatma gandhi that
and i
you know what my opinion is about mr
gandhi
i said that his contribution i think i
said i don't remember exactly what i
said but they were all aghast mr
sudhinder kulkarni said that he was
aghast
that i expressed this sort of opinion
about mr gandhi
and what is striking what is so so
remarkable
is that even the pakistanis have so much
respect and love for mr gandhi
isn't that curious
it is one thing to see to expect that
indians many indians would
have a great deal of respect and
admiration for mr gandhi but you will
see even more admiration for mr gandhi
among the pakistanis
why is that so have you ever asked
yourself this why do the pakistanis love
mr gandhi more than indians
isn't that strange so uh that was my
experience i was
i was on one side everybody was against
me in that in that panel
they were all peaceniks they all wanted
peace between india and pakistan but
apparently on the terms of pakistan not
on the terms of india and they were all
big fans of mr gandhi and they all
believed that mr gandhi gave india its
independence and mr bose had nothing to
do with it
mr ishtaria i think he said that
he did not do anything that sort of
thing you know
so that was my experience would i be
collaborating with mr ahmed again
no mercy
okay
what else do we have
is it true that the cheras cholas and
pandias were the longest surviving
kingdoms on earth
the cholas are one of the one of the
longest ruling dynasties in human
history
so uh they're
they're they're uh
they are first attested sometime in the
second or third century bc
okay and at that time they were small
rulers but their existence as rulers in
southern india
in a small part of southern india
southern india is attested from that
time
and they continued on as small local
kings
for over a thousand years
until
the cusp of the 10th and 11th centuries
a.d
when they suddenly became an enormous
empire
under
and his son the great rajendra chula he
who conquered essentially the whole of
southeast asia
so their
reign their rule as a dynasty
lasted approximately 1500 years roughly
roughly give or take a little bit
so i would say that the cholas
are
possibly the longest
ruling dynasty in the history of
humanity
i am not sure if there is any any other
dynasty maybe i don't remember but
certainly the cholas i'm not sure about
the cheras and pandyas if they ruled
that long probably not but the cholas
are like incredible
all right
let's have some interesting questions
ladies and gentlemen
um
was cm jyoti bashu a bad guy
well
one guy's terrorist is another guy's
freedom fighter so it all depends on
your perspective
whether he was a bad guy or a great guy
it all depends on your political
inclinations and your perspective that's
what i can say but if you want to
if you want to have an objective measure
of
the effect of his rule look at the
economic performance of bengal during
the time he was chief minister
how much development did bengal see how
much did bengal's economy grow how many
new industries came up what was the
overall living standards in bengal
if you if you ask yourself these
questions
well that will give you a very good
indication numeric
tangible measurable
measure of his performance as a chief
minister
and then look at the kind of
policies he implemented and what was the
kind of attitude he had towards the
opposition parties what sort of policies
did he implement i think it's all out
there in the public domain
and what sort of uh attitude he had
towards
towards indian foreign policy especially
relations with china and all that it's
very clear what it was he was communist
and he was very much pro-china
so based on all of that i will leave it
to all of you to determine
decide for yourself
using your own
innate intelligence whether he was a
good guy bad guy good good leader bad
leader good cm bad cm what sort of
performance he had
what's your view on netaji's spiritual
accomplishments
he saw all this before we did
yeah i don't know i don't know about his
spiritual accomplishments i know him as
a freedom fighter as a great son of
india as a warrior
as a great leader i don't know about his
spiritual accomplishments
i don't know sorry
uh
okay what else do we have uh i'm sure
there are lots of interesting questions
what is the origin of fair-skinned
people in india the origin of
fair-skinned people in india is indian
pop is the indian population
the gene
for fair skin
originated either in india or the middle
east
now if you look at the middle east
geographically it is part of the
extended indian subcontinent and it has
been part of the
overall indian population continuum in
history in the past 10 000 years
right so the origin of
fair skin
its itself in india the europeans got
this gene for fair skin
from
indians
now you know
i think by now we all know
that
the modern european population
is the descendants
are the modern europeans most of them
are descended from
an older european population the hunter
gatherers etc
farmers
they're females and
the invading yamnaya males
these invaders are called yamnaya it's a
russian term which means pit
but these invading males
who were all horse riding brutal
warriors
they all came from the east
and their genetic haplogroup lineage is
r1b which is
99.9 percent now known to be of indian
origin
right
so the fair skin not only in india but
also in europe originates from a genetic
mutation
that first occurred in india about seven
eight five between five and ten thousand
years before today so that's the origin
of fair skin
not only in india but also in europe
and maybe i can maybe i can even show
you if
i can fair skin mutation
let me
try and google it
[Music]
let's take a look at
so
okay this this gene genetic mutation
which
okay it's a long paper i will not be
able to identify the exact clauses in
there but
there you have it
indians and europeans share
light-skinned genetic mutation
and that mutation yes slc whatever it is
it actually originated in india or the
middle east and the middle east is an
extension of the indian genetic
population in ancient times
so there you have it you can do your own
research and look it up a little look it
up in more detail
okay
next what other questions do we have
what other questions do we have
um
where ancient indians mostly vegetarians
well it depends on which time period
you're looking at
uh if you look at the archaeological
evidence in ancient india you find
evidence of fish hooks of harpoons of
spears
with
those
indentations on them which indicate they
are not for warfare but for hunting
you also find evidence of bones with cut
marks on them and all that
so clearly there were
there were time periods in indian
history
when indians were at least some indians
ate meat for sure
but at some point in time because of our
culture civilization and because we
became so developed that there was no
need to eat meat
at some point in time
maybe during the vedic age or
thereabouts
this idea did come into our culture
that non-violence is the highest ideal
as far as possible it should not hurt
any other living being
and therefore vegetarianism is the
superior way of living
but i would say at any given point in
time even during the vedic age there
would have been people who ate meat
and you find evidence of that
but i would say that after the vedic age
maybe the majority of indians may have
been vegetarians
possibly but not all it's never been all
india has always been a very very
diverse
culture very diverse civilization so
even among the people
who
were members of vedic culture and
civilization there would have been
people who eat meat
i know this is not going to be make me
very popular
but facts are facts you find evidence in
the archaeological record of meat eating
at various in various periods of indian
history
so meat eating was there but
vegetarianism was also certainly there
if we are able to free tibet
can we make it part of india
let's free free tibet first and then
we'll decide so we freed bangladesh from
pakistan and see what we did with it
we made it a separate country and now
it's
well you know what the situation is
so
the fur the biggest question is ah
will we be able to free tibet from the
chinese
it is very much in india's national
interest to have a free tibet
a non-chinese tibet on our northern
border right so it is very much
something that we should
accomplish
in the long term
it would be good for our national
security and our national interest
so the first thing is to free tibet and
then we can decide whether to make it a
free country or make it a part of india
that that is something that will be
thought about later
the real question is
can we free tibet if yes how can we do
it and in what time frame can we do it
so that is the real deal that's the real
question
uh
tibet claimed ladakh no
nope
it is the taiwanese who claimed the dark
not tibet
okay what else we have whatever else we
have
shikkar sarov says in india we see many
cases like sushruta saying his knowledge
has been delivered
from his lord
dhanvatri and ramanujan saying his math
came from a goddess how do we explain
this well everybody has their own
personal views about how the how they
got their knowledge
and we have to respect people's views
right
so
i i personally don't have an explanation
of why some people believe that their
knowledge scientific knowledge comes
from a goddess or a god or whatever
everybody has a personal belief system
there are so many scientists who are
very religious
there are so many christian scientists
who believe in jesus christ there are
jesus physicists there are there are
jewish physicists who practice judaism
who believe in the judaic
god and all that abrahamic god
so
so it is not uncommon
for scientists and mathematicians
to have religious inclinations and
religious beliefs
and when you have religious beliefs you
may attribute
your discovery of whatever knowledge you
have discovered to divine
influence
so that is a personal thing there is no
need to explain it in some way
right
it's a personal thing
so that's what i can say about it some
people are atheistic and this is it has
come from me only from my own intellect
some people will say it's come from a
god or goddess or the gods
or the brahman or whatever it's a matter
of personal belief
um
okay here's a question why does india
not have dual citizenship
is it disadvantageous in any way will it
cause security threats as some claim
yeah it can cause security problems
let's say you have i mean you can
certainly exclude certain countries from
the dual citizenship clause
for instance you may say that people of
chinese origin or pakistani origin or
whatever are not allowed to become dual
citizens but then there's always other
problems for instance you have the case
of this guy david coleman
headley
who was one of the principal uh
terrorist investigators who did all the
reconnaissance
before the
uh
2611 terrorist attack in mumbai right so
his name was david coleman headley he
was an american citizen
but
his father was pakistani
right so he was half pakistani
and his actual name was some gilani or
something but he changed his name
legally in the u.s to david coleman
hadley hadley to make it make it look
like he was not off he had nothing to do
with pakistan
and imagine if somebody like that gets
dual citizenship with india they'll be
able to
to wreak all kinds of havoc in india so
we already have so much foreign
influence in india we have so much
of all this going on so why take extra
unnecessary risks so maybe in the future
when when india becomes a really
powerful country then we can open up
dual citizenship for certain
nationalities but as of today i think it
is very dangerous
even if you
allow only certain countries to have
dual citizenship even then you may have
people like david coleman headley
uh
filtering in and
you know
hurting india's national interest so i
think that's the reason why
at least india doesn't have this
clause of dual citizenship
will china be able to cut the chicken's
neck with the held of nepal pakistan and
bangladesh in the future
it is a possibility but then india can
also take certain actions
see if you look at see this is a
question i've answered lots of times
first of all but i'll take it again so
if this is the chicken neck you're
talking about the siliguri corridor
right so if the chinese
manage to cut it off it means that we
will lose access to the northeast so
what we can do is very simple go through
bangladesh
in times of war we don't need to respect
the sovereignty of other nations
when our own national security is at
stake
so if this chinese succeed by whatever
means to cut off in cutting of the
chicken's neck the siliguri corridor we
can just go straight through bangladesh
and re-establish our
communications over lines of
supplies everything with the north east
very simple
and if the nepalese
i don't think the nepalese would get
involved in this but if there is any
nepalese involvement in this then they
will have to pay a price in in the long
run for this for what did what they do
so it is possible
perhaps there is a small probability
that the chinese may be able to do that
but we have lots of options in that case
we can simply cut through bangladesh and
re-establish our connection or
connectivity and supply routes and all
that logistical routes
with the northeast of india so it's not
a big problem once you think in a
different way
okay what else do we have
sad
sad guru believes in the aryan invasion
theory please do a collab with him
and show him new evidences
okay thank you for the suggestion
[Music]
what else do we have what happened at
theater men's square in 1989 in china
there was a massacre
there was this pro-independence movement
pro-democracy not independence
pro-democracy movement
uh
tens of thousands of students who were
who were protesting demonstrating
men's square in beijing you want to look
at it let's take a look at it
let's see what tiananmen square looks
like this is the city of beijing
and
if you go into beijing i'm not sure
quite where it is but i am sure we can
search for it
kiananmen square
so here it is this is tiananmen square
it's where that horrific massacre took
place
i think it's somewhere here
tiananmen square this is what they call
it
so it's here that this this
demonstration took place all these
students tens of thousands of students
they demonstrated there for days in
favor of democracy
and eventually the chinese communist
party ordered a military crackdown on
them with tanks and machine guns and all
kinds of weaponry
and there are a number of versions of
what happened the chinese say that maybe
70 80 100 200 people died the western
media claims that 10 000 20 000 people
died the students
we don't know exactly where the truth
lies maybe it's somewhere in between
and the chinese allege that it is it was
a western attempt at regime change which
is something that is actually quite
plausible the west has be has a long
history of trying to influence
uh
events in various countries and
interfere in various countries internal
affairs
so that's what happened in tiananmen
square in the chinese communist party
after two or three days they cracked
down and they said enough is enough we
will not tolerate this and there was a
bloody massacre lots of people died and
that's that's that's what happened in
1989 in tiananmen square
didn't i answer this okay let's take it
again what if china gives pakistan
hypersonic missile technology in order
to counter india's purchase of s 400
missile system
why is the west lagging behind
developing hypersonic missiles the west
is indeed kind of lagging behind
uh the best hypersonic missiles are the
russian missiles the russian sircon
missiles which uh
which have a maximum speed of max seven
or eight or something which is
ridiculously fast
so i don't think any western system has
a defend has a defense against a missile
of that speed
which essentially means that various uh
the british
elizabeth class aircraft carriers
etcetera are already obsolete
so uh
so yes the west is kind of lagging
behind in missile technology the
americans are now trying to catch up
they have a number of hypersonic missile
programs
uh the chinese have this df dongfeng
some number
hypersonic missile which they have
developed
it's called a carrier killer missile
it's a ballistic missile
which could
take out an entire aircraft carrier
battle group or something
we're not sure how accurate it is but
they seem to have some such technology
they also have a
hyper maneuvering
vehicle
that they tested recently
so yes they do have some such technology
and what if they give it to pakistan
well then india will have to do
something about it
right
so the response so what should india do
about this develop its own
technology india right now is doing
remarkably well
in developing and testing
better and better
missile systems
right and this is a consequence of all
the support that drdo etc has got from
the government in the last seven to
eight years
right now you see lots of missile tests
happening if you want to improve a
missile system or rocket system you need
to do lots and lots of tests and you see
lots of tests happening in the last
couple of years
so i am sure there are certain missile
systems that are being developed in
india that are very secret and that have
not been revealed to the public
so i am quite certain we are developing
our own hypersonic missiles and even if
we have developed them by now we will
not announce it to the world
unless there is a need to do that
so
the
response to such a development is very
simple india has to develop its own
technology and i'm sure we are doing
that
all right
yes it is uh
where is that comment the comments they
move so fast
df-17 yes sir you're right thank you
that's the chinese hypersonic missile
the uh carrier killer missile
the df-17 the dongfeng 17.
all right
yeah this is a question i get a almost
every time what are my thoughts on you
all
know our harare's work like sapiens and
homo deus
he said in his book
they agree that the agricultural
revolution was a curse for human
civilization so my answer even today has
not changed i still haven't read that
book the two books
i have those books
in another place
i have both the books
i have so many books that i still
haven't read
my my reading list is more than 100
books long that is my reading backlog
it's gonna take me
years to finish that
so yeah one of those books hopefully i
will read is one of these
harari books but since i haven't read
these two books i really can't comment
about it
when i do read them i will answer this
question
okay
what else do we have
okay let's see this
so avid alternative says did there ever
exist an entity in india like the
hashishins
hashishins of arabia
or the ninjas of japan the hashishins
were not exactly arabic i think they
were shias
shias in persia and the middle east
the fortress of alamout
during the time of salahuddin ayubi
and
those centuries
and they were eventually
wiped out eradicated
by the great shri chingish khan and his
descendants so uh that's about the
hashishins they were alleged to
carry out assassinations political
assassinations paid assassinations
under the influence of drugs hashish
that's why they are believed to have
been called the hashishins
now in japan they had these
professional assassins called the ninjas
they had their entire martial art called
ninjutsu
they operated in the shadows under the
cloak of anonymity and they carried out
political assassinations
on behalf of various whoever paid them
especially essentially
so did there ever exist such an entity
in india
there must have existed entities like
that in india in ancient times
if you
read the arthashastra
which whose author is vishnu gupta
chanakya from the mauryan empire era
well there is certainly uh there are
mentions of uh
the use of political assassinations of
of assassins of spies and all of these
things
in the service
of the nation
and the empire and the civilization so
the emperor needs to ensure that
the entire country is safe and there are
no
enemies of the nation proliferating and
all that that's why you need to take
certain actions you need to do certain
things you need to spy
on the general uh
population i suppose
and in case there are certain
enemies of the nation you have to take
them out
quietly
so yes
there were assassins in those days
employed by the states
so i'm not sure what they were called in
all that but certainly
any
powerful emperor empress king queen
would have employed the services of
professional assassins you need that
to safeguard
the country and the citizens and the
civilization you need that
but uh so yeah it certainly did exist
and you can see uh references to that in
the arthashastra
okay what else do we have
um
what else do we have illuminati
are the illuminati real please answer
well i haven't come across any of them
in real life so i can't say for sure
so there is this persistent story
persistent claim
there's a secret society that kind of
controls the world it's called the
illuminati
well
where's the evidence it doesn't mean see
because we don't have evidence it
doesn't mean that this secret society or
any other secret society doesn't exist
secret societies have always existed
but
are they real
we don't know i i personally don't have
answers right
um
to whom should we give the title of
father of of the nation if we could well
first of all why do we need a father of
the nation
certainly not mr mohammed as gandhi
see today there is this uh
there is this
attempt
which is made
this idea of india attempt which is made
to make indians believe that india was
born in 1947
and the so-called founding fathers of
india
are the people who framed the
constitution on all that
those are not the founding fathers of
india india was not born in 1947. the
truncated mediocre nation state of india
was indeed born in 1947 but the
civilization state of india has existed
for ten thousand plus years
so if you were to give the title of
father of nation to somebody it would be
somebody like lord ram or lord krishna
or the great emperor bharat after whom
the civilization is named bharat
so somebody like that
certainly not a mediocre little person
like the mr like mr gandhi certainly not
mr gandhi
okay let's take some more questions
is there a question
or you want mr vivekananda to be the
father of the nation i don't think he's
that great
to be the father of the nation india is
a 10 000 plus year-old civilization you
need somebody bigger than mr vivekananda
to be the father of the nation i am not
saying he is insignificant or any such
thing i'm not passing any judgment
on mr vivekananda i am saying there have
been far far greater people than mr
vivekananda in india
right so i would not agree
with anyone who says that mr that swami
vivekananda should be the father of the
nation certainly not come on
okay this is an interesting question i'm
not sure if i have taken this before so
let's take it
anime says
if we already had trade routes
established as far as rome for thousands
of years
why did vasco de gama and christopher
columbus venture out on a sea voyage
hoping to find india well there is a gap
in your knowledge of history which let
me fill let me feel it this is the good
question
so what happened like you said it is
well known that we had trade routes
trade connections with rome about 2000
years ago we find ample evidence of that
archaeological evidence in india and in
rome in in italy as well
this is established beyond any doubt
that there was there were ex extensive
trade connections between india and rome
so that trade happened why i see where
the sea routes and and then possibly
wire land routes also
in rome as you can see is here in italy
and india as you can see is all the way
here thousands of kilometers away so
what happened what happened is that so
let me let me explain what happened in
the 13th century a new phenomenon
emerged
in asia that phenomenon was called ching
is khan the great sri chingis khan the
great mongol conqueror who conquered
half the world the greatest conqueror in
known history and he suddenly expanded
out of mongolia and
and what happened as a consequence of
that is that the turks the turkic tribes
they all ran from him they were scared
for their life they ran ran ran
westwards trying to escape the mongol
empire and its expansion
so they used to uh live somewhere around
the gobi desert
right
and then they ran from there they ran
westwards
and they kept running running running
they came to central asia they kept
running westwards and from central asia
from the caucasus region
they came southwards and they entered
anatolia
and eventually after
and they established their small
kingdoms there and that eventually
became the ottoman empire which
destroyed the byzantine empire which was
here in turkey whose capital was
constantinople
and the turks
conquered constantinople
which year was that
look it up i think 1500 and something
14 something
which year did they conquer
constantinople i don't remember the date
exactly
but it was a mahmoud
fatih
the ottoman sultan who conquered
constantinople and the effect that had
is that all the trade routes with india
were cut off
so the trade routes were over land
routes between europe and india the
europeans needed indian spices and
indian products and in exchange for that
they used to export gold to india
now the turks conquered constantinople
they conquered the byzantine empire
and they were hostile to the europeans
they were hostile to the christians they
were all muslims the turks right
so that had the effect of cutting off
the trade routes with india
and then the europeans stopped getting
the spices and whatever else they needed
from india and that is why they started
looking for other routes
for reaching india
and that's how vasco de gama and
christopher columbus went in very
different directions looking for india
columbus the great idiot thought that he
will reach india by going
westwards and he reached the americas
and he thought that was india that's why
he called the natives
indians
vasquez went south
and he went around the cape of good hope
and that's where
in eastern africa he came across various
indian people
and they brought him to india
so that's what happened so that is the
reason why
even though there were these historic
trade routes between india and europe
especially rome greece all that
but because the turks
cut off the trade routes
a few centuries before today that's why
the europeans were forced to look for
alternate
uh
ways to reach india it's essentially a
sea a sea route towards india so that's
why christopher columbus moscow the
government et cetera they all went
looking for india
and vasquez succeeded columbus
discovered america by mistake
so interesting question
um
okay let's see some other things
does china respect indian culture and
indian people or do they hate us like
the westerners
the chinese look upon india as a
colonized
broken inferior mediocre country and
they are correct in their assessment
the chinese don't respect india today
they have deep contempt for india today
and they show india as an example of
what happens when you become too
democratic and you when you try to copy
the west
and they are absolutely right about this
look at the development in china and
look at the development in india
it's very simple there's a stark
difference
the
divergence between the trajectories of
india and china since the 1990s is
incredibly stark
they got their act together and they
have taken off in a very
uh
on this direction of extreme economic
growth right
and look at india still mediocre still
corrupt still bogged down
in bureaucracy and federalism and all
that
so the chinese today the chinese
communist party
displays india as an example of
mediocrity
and an example of what happens when you
have democracy in western values in a
country in an asian country
they don't hate india
and historically the chinese considered
india to be the center of heaven so
before india was broken before india was
occupied by the turks
and then by the by the europeans
when india was still free the chinese
had the greatest of respect and
admiration from india for india
there was one way transfer of culture
and civilization from india to china
there is absolutely no transfer of
chinese values chinese culture and
chinese traditions chinese religion
values anything into india
but if you look at chinese history in
the past
1500 years or so you will see so much of
indian culture that has been transferred
into china and they were thankful for it
they used to send their monks and
travelers to india to get more texts
vedic texts buddhist texts philosophical
texts spiritual texts
and they used to request indian kings to
send indian scholars to china
and that's how you have people like
nagarjuna
bodhi dharma the great dhyana master and
the father of kung fu etc
so china gained so much from india and
they had so much respect for india they
that they called india tianjin the
center of heaven
today india is a different country india
is no longer a dharmic country today
india is a broken
mentally colonized mediocre country of
low standards unfortunately
it is still a nation of great people but
the people don't realize their greatness
so today china thinks of india as a
mediocre country they don't hate india
they simply have a great deal of
contempt for india
and they are quite justified in that
so my message to all of you is please
raise your standards you have greatness
in your ancestry you all have greatness
in your genetics in your blood
please rediscover this greatness
raise your standards
reject mediocrity
okay
shashank says is information rather than
energy the basic constituent of reality
could all elementary particles observed
be quantized manifestations of
information
embedded inside god consciousness so
until the last two words you were
talking science now you're talking
spirituality
you know there is something called
information theory
which actually can be a good
representation of reality as we see it
so it is
certainly a very
worthwhile and a very serious
uh
avenue for
scientific investigation and research
theoretical physics
and also in computer science so this is
where computer science kind of
uh converges with theoretical physics in
information theory especially in black
hole physics and all that you have a
great deal of
applications of information theory
entropy
and all that
so it is certainly possible that
information rather than energy could be
the basic constituent of reality
yes but i don't know about god
consciousness god now see
god is spirituality and philosophy it is
not science so let's not merge the two
things i
have the greatest of respect
for
philosophy for spirituality for religion
especially
indian civilization and dharmic culture
and religion okay
but from a scientific perspective we
don't discuss god it's as simple as that
how do you define god consciousness from
from the perspective of physics you
simply cannot
forget about god consciousness you can't
even define human consciousness from the
perspective of physics or science
so when you have something that is not a
scientific concept you cannot mix it
with science it's it's just like that
right
so to answer the first part of the
question it is certainly possible yes
that information could be the basis of
reality
what bhushan says what happened
if russia invaded ukraine
and why putin wants to invade ukraine
okay so there is the situation going on
right now in ukraine there is this big
russian military presence on the borders
of ukraine
vladimir putin
is essentially threatening to invade why
is it so
it's because
russia considers ukraine
and the former ussr republics
to be part of its
geopolitical sphere of influence and to
be part of its red lines now if nato
which essentially is nothing but the u.s
tries to influence ukraine and if
ukraine won't tries to become a part of
nato that will cross the
the russian red lines
so that's what mr putin is saying
that if
the west tries to influence ukraine and
tries to interfere in ukraine beyond a
certain point there's gonna be war
that's the red line you cannot cross
and the west essentially the us is
trying to test
mr putin's red lines so that's where we
are right now
so if the west
persists
in crossing the red lines
then you may you may end up seeing a
russian invasion of ukraine and then
we'll have to see how nato responds
nato the european union essentially are
just puppets of the us
you can consider them to be
if you want to put it crudely
vasal states of the united states
so uh mr putin doesn't really want to
invade ukraine but he has to draw
certain red lines if you don't resp if
you don't draw and respect your own red
lines then people are going to keep on
en encroaching into your sphere of
influence and eventually you become
powerless and you will lose all
sovereignty
so that's why the situation currently
exists
and it could
it could turn into a big
conflagration possibly if
certain things happen if certain actions
are taken
all right
okay how can you be sure about india
being the original founder zone when
india and
even iran and persia are closer to
africa okay first of all iran and persia
are not two different things they're the
same thing
and how am i sure about india being the
original founder zone because we have
archaeological evidence and we have
genetic evidence
the genetic evidence is the diversity
of genetics that you find in india
india has the highest genetic diversity
and the oldest genetic lineages outside
of africa that proves that india is the
original founder zone now these are some
some basic simple concepts of genetics
that you have to understand in order to
understand the argument i'm making and
the facts i'm presenting before you
so
any region which has high genetic
diversity
indicates
a high genetic diversity indicates
presence of
population for a longer time
the higher the diversity the older the
population it's as simple as that there
is a basic fundamental law in genetics
so india in the entire world on the
entire planet has the second highest
genetic diversity in the world outside
of africa
and the oldest genetic lineages outside
of africa which demonstrates
that india is the original out of africa
founder zone
sure iran persia is closer to africa and
yet the highest diversity is in india
why
because persia
essentially if you look at the terrain
and all that
it was a desert at the time only the
coastal coastal regions had vegetation
but the indian subcontinent was rich it
was lush
it had beautiful climate it had fertile
soil it had a great deal of vegetation
it could sustain a large population so
after all these migrations after this
long migration the first place where
humanity settled down properly was the
indian subcontinent
so we have genetic evidence for that we
also have archaeological evidence for
that that goes back 70 plus thousand
years
right
so the indian population which settled
down the the human population that
settled down in india at the time it was
able to survive the toba volcanic
explosion
the volcanic eruption of the toba
volcano which was an enormously
cataclysmic event
the indian population was able to
survive that there is genetic there is
archaeological evidence also for that so
based on all of this evidence
i am able to say to all of you that
india is the original out of africa
founder zone
and i would encourage all of you to do a
little bit of your own research all the
information is available in the public
domain look up some genetic research
papers archaeological research papers
not wikipedia but actual research
and you will see
what i'm i've been saying all this time
and otherwise
uh listen to some experts
so on tuesday
the third episode of my podcast is going
to
uh premiere on this channel it is with
dr neeraj rai who is one of the world's
leading experts in archaeogenetics in
population genetics and molecular
biology if you don't believe me listen
to him listen to what he has to say
right
shubham says is russia really india's
friends really india's friend listen my
dear friends
you and me we can be friends
but in geopolitics there are no friends
there are
allies and adversaries
alliances are temporary adversarial
relationships are also temporary
everything is temporary in geopolitics
there are no friendships in geopolitics
if you believe somebody is your friend
you are the stupidest person in the
world i'm not saying this person to
anyone i'm just saying that as somebody
who is a national leader
if you believe
as the head of your nation that somebody
is your friend you are the silliest
person in the world
there are no friendships in geopolitics
all right
so india and russia have very good
relations
and historically over the past 60 70
plus years we have had excellent
relations with russia with the ussr but
see how things changed after the 1990s
all that warmth disappeared
especially during the
regime of mr boris yeltsin the russians
essentially abandoned india
right
today under mr vladimir putin there is a
much better understanding of each
other's situation
and there is again a significant
convergence of interests
things are complicated of course there
is china in the way russia needs china
more than india right now
because of the actions of the us
but
in the long run russia and india are
closer allies in my opinion than the
russia china relationship so
what i would say is that there are no
friendships no friendships in
geopolitics indians
don't understand this oh we love this
country we love that country they are
our friends come on
for instance let me give an example
indians have this great love for some
reason for israel
i also admire israel israel is a very
admirable country
but loving that country
come on
see
try and examine in israel's geopolitical
moves
they tried their best to become allies
with china
10 15 years ago it is the americans that
prevented them from doing it the chinese
were very interested in in israeli
technology weapon systems and the
israelis are very happy to sell it to
china for money
the americans
prevented israel from doing this
after that india and israel's relations
grew much better
after that
so is is israel india's friend or is it
an alliance of convenience ask
yourselves
personally
admire the israeli people
but it doesn't mean that we should start
loving the nation of israel and thinking
they are our friends it's not friendship
it's an alliance
because our interests currently align
but it is not going to remain this way
forever things may change
so please look at the world from a
realistic perspective not from an
idealistic emotional perspective this is
something indians need to learn please
learn this my dear friends
uh what was the question i saw something
else okay
what could be the philosophical reason
for the decline of bharat the decline of
bharat is not a philosophical decline
it's a material decline and therefore
the religion the reasons are also
material
the decline of bharat
happened in the past 1000 years
why did it happen it's because we
allowed
barbarians to invade and occupy us
now i am not calling somebody barbarians
because of their religion or their blood
or their ancestry i am calling people
barbarians based on their actions
okay
so the turks
because of their actions in india were
barbarians in my opinion
the europeans because of their actions
in india genocide destruction
plunder they were also barbarians so
why did india
decline the way it did in the past 1000
years because these barbarians caught us
at the wrong time when there was a lack
of political unity in india
if india was unified under a single
political system let's say under
somebody like chandragupta maurya or
kanishka
or
or skanda gupta or kumar gupta or some
other gupta or under the cholas if they
have they had been able to unify the
whole of india then this would not have
happened so the
reason for the decline of bharat is
that we were undergoing
a phase a period when we were fragmented
when you had lots of small kingdoms
who did not fight together
in uh destroying
in defeating
the foreign invaders so there is no
philosophical reason for it it's it's a
simple political reason
when you are united and we when you have
a strong
centralized system nobody can defeat you
when you are weak when you are a soft
state when you have political disunity
like you have today
you can again be colonized so that's the
reason why we were
by why our civilization declined
okay
else do we have do we have anything else
what
who is single
are aliens present in conca la pass in
ladakh well i'll go and find out all
right
i would love to go and find out
and i hope they are double vaccinated in
their wearing masks i hope so
uh
who is george soros why is he
interfering in indian indian internal
matters
george soros is an alien
and he has been allowed alive for about
2000 years i think and
he is interfering in india on behalf of
of
a secret society i guess
listen i don't know man i don't know
okay where else are we do we have
anything um
any other questions
there are of course hundreds of
questions
excuse me
listen
i would appreciate better language
consider this to be a warning sir please
don't
do
this okay let me take a couple more
questions before we're done
my views on achara prashanth prashant i
i am not uh
familiar with this gentleman so
unfortunately i can't say
uh my views on dr ambedkar vista versus
mr gandhi i think dr ambedkar's views on
mr gandhi are very very
very inconvenient
mr ambedkar had the profoundest contempt
for mr gandhi and it is very clear in
the writings of mr ambedkar
so you can look that up it's very
interesting to read
all right
okay where do we what else do we have do
we have anything uh
if the childhood of a great leader is
very immoral will it hurt the country's
image
should a leader's past matter if they
changed from what they were in the
childhood
why are we concerned about the nation's
image
what what really matters is not how
other people perceive you
what matters is how powerful you are how
independent you are how prosperous you
are and what sort of living standards
and governance you have
your image doesn't matter who cares what
the british think of us or the french
think of us
who cares what the arabs think of us
it doesn't matter
it is not of any importance what anyone
thinks of the country's image
if you are prosperous and powerful your
image is
the greatest no matter what sort of
uh leader you have or whatever and and
i'll tell you something
a leader's personal life typically
doesn't matter
look at the the father of turkey mustafa
kemal ataturk one of the greatest
leaders of the 20th century
a man
who
brought turkey back from the brink of
destruction
who fought against foreign occupation
and who won
mustafa
one of the greatest generals
in military history and one of the
greatest leaders of the 20th century if
you look at his personal life he was a
terrible human being
he had no friends he was an alcoholic he
drank himself to death
he had no friends
the way he treated women was
terrible
but
he dedicated his entire life to the
service of his country that cannot be
denied he was not a good
person from a personal perspective but
as a leader
the turks could not have asked the gods
for any better leader so you know what
it doesn't matter what sort of personal
life a leader lives as long
what what really matters is
does he or she serve the country
effectively or not that's all that
matters so a leader's past doesn't
matter a leader's personal life doesn't
matter all that matters is whether he or
she carries out his duty or her duty as
a leader effectively or not that's all
that matters
all right
okay i think that brings us to the end
of today's session thank you so much
this was a very interesting session very
interesting question some of them
so wonderful great great fun
and we shall continue doing this
so next week
a couple of new podcasts will make their
appearance on this channel
and we shall continue this q a sessions
going forward as always
so until then until until then
take care thank you everyone thank you
very much
i appreciate your questions i thank you
for your viewership and your support
and i will see you very soon take care
bye